<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The second oration of Master Theodore de Beze, minister of the holy gospel, made and pronounced at Poussy, in the open assemblye of [ye] prelates of Fraunce, in the prese[n]ce of the Quene, mother, and princes of the bloud ryal. The. xxvi. day of Septe[m]ber. Anno. 1561</title>
            <title>Seconde harangue de M. Théodore de Besze. English.</title>
            <author>Bèze, Théodore de, 1519-1605.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1562</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10028</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 2028</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109011</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844662</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844662</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9495</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10028)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9495)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 174:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The second oration of Master Theodore de Beze, minister of the holy gospel, made and pronounced at Poussy, in the open assemblye of [ye] prelates of Fraunce, in the prese[n]ce of the Quene, mother, and princes of the bloud ryal. The. xxvi. day of Septe[m]ber. Anno. 1561</title>
                  <title>Seconde harangue de M. Théodore de Besze. English.</title>
                  <author>Bèze, Théodore de, 1519-1605.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ihon Tysdale, and are to be solde at his shoppe, in the vpper ende of Lombarde strete, in Alhallowes churchyeard, nere vnto grace church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1562?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Bèze, Théodore de. La seconde harangue de M. Théodore de Besze, .. prononcée à Poissy, en pleine assemblée des prélats de France, en la présence de la royne mère et princes du sang, .. le vingt-sixiesme jour du mois de septembre 1561.</note>
                  <note>Publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Colloquy of Poissy (1561) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Charles IX, 1560-1574 --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  Religious history --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9495:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9495:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>¶ The ſecond ORATION OF</hi> MA<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter Theodore de Beze, Miniſter of the holy Goſpel, made and pronounced at Poyſſy, in the open aſſemblye of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lates of Fraunce, in the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the Quene, mother, and Princes of the bloud ryal. The .xxvi. day of Septe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber. Anno .1561.</p>
            <p>¶Imprynted at London, by Ihon Tyſdale, and are to be ſolde at his ſhoppe, in the vpper ende of Lombarde ſtrete, in Alhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes churchyeard, nere vnto grace church.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="oration">
            <pb facs="tcp:9495:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9495:2"/>
            <head>Oration.</head>
            <p>MAdame, the laſt tyme that it pleaſed you too geue vs audience, we made declaration as God gaue vs grace, of the article, whiche was propounde, as touchinge the churche, the markes, tokens and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities of theſame: wherein we folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, ſo the worde of God, that euery man, as we thinke, had occaſion too be content with our au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwer. But in ſtead of approuing, that whiche we ſpake or reprouing that, which deſerued correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it was aſked vs, by what power we did miniſter the worde of God, and the holy ſacraments. And therupon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge was ſpared to make oure cauſe more odious. We knowe not to what intent that was moued &amp; ſet forward. For fyrſte we haue not preſented oure ſelues heare to miniſter the woorde of God, nor the holy ſacraments, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it neded nothing at al to aſke vs bi what power or autority we wold do it. If thei ſay vnto vs that it is to make vs render, a reaſon or cauſe of that whiche we haue done in tyme paſte, it behoued
<pb facs="tcp:9495:3"/>
then too conſyder that the ſtate of oure companye is of two maner of men: the one ſerues for minyſters oute of this realme, and in place where there vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is receaued. Of thoſe it canne not be aſked whye they are miniſters. There are other that preach in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme, whome you haue not called too geue a reaſon of that is paſt, as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge theyr vocation, but onely to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre of theyr doctrin otherwiſe it ſhuld be a begynninge of theyr proces, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon we are aſſured, Madame, that you neuer thoughte nor ment. If it be by a maner of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference, vnder correction it wer to no great purpoſe and could not ſerue but to make vs enter ſo farre into this matter that we ſhoulde noteaſely come out without offendinge my Lords the prelates, whiche thinge we mente not, neyther wyll we geue occaſion to anye man to interrupte this holye and Chriſtian worke nowe begon. And to thyntente men maye knowe that we ſpeake not without greate reaſon at euerye tyme that two parties come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb facs="tcp:9495:3"/>
too enter in to conference if one aſke by what power or autority do you this or that, the other wyll aſke him the like, and ſo it ſhall be a hard thinge if vppon theeſe queſtions there riſe not ſome diſcention.</p>
            <p>Nowe leauinge my Lordes the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates of this realme whom we will not offend: let vs admit that a biſhop ſhuld aſke vs, vnder what tytle preache and adminiſter you the holy ſacramentes? We woulde aſke him whether he were choſen of the auncientes of the churche to whome he is appoynted for a biſhop, whether he haue bene required by the people: If their were anye informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before, of his lyfe, maners, and doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, he wold ſay, yea, but men know the contrarye: and we remitte it to the conſcience of the hart of thoſe that hear vs, whiche knowe how the matter go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. Nowe if he ſayde vnto vs. You are no miniſters becauſe ye haue not the impoſition of handes we ſhoulde aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere them. Ye are not miniſters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that in inſtitutinge you, are lefte
<pb facs="tcp:9495:4"/>
out the ſubſtantiall poynts commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the canon lawe which can not be diſpenſed with all. And if the diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhoulde wax hoter, we would goe further, and mighte vſe ſuche woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. You haue but one of the three poynts requiſite in the inſtitution, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is the layinge on of handes. If the lack of that ſame depriue vs from being miniſters: for the lacke of the other two you ſhal be no more miniſter than we.</p>
            <p>The councyle of Calcedone, whiche is one of the foure generalles, orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth that: <hi>irrita ſit ordinatio:</hi> of that prieſt whiche was not appoynted ſpeciallye for the ſeruice of ſome churche, <hi>irrita,</hi> ſayethe it, <hi>in iniuriam ordinantis:</hi> By a ſtronger reaſonne we maye ſaye to the byſhoppe that thus woulde dyſpute wyth vs, whan the twoo eſſentyall poyntes bee awaye agaynſte the ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of the Apoſtell .1. <hi>Timoth</hi> .3. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.6. yet here is an other poynt whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che greueth vs ſore to ſpeake, &amp; yet we are conſtrained to it, to thintent to ſhew vnto all this companye, that if this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putinge
<pb facs="tcp:9495:4"/>
of vocation were ones opened, it ſhoulde be verye daungerous. If we ſhould of the ſayde biſhoppe, demaunde who gaue him this laying on of hands, he woulde ſay the biſhoppes by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tority that was geuen them. And if we ſhoulde aſke him, for how muche haue you boughte this authoritye? He woulde ſaye that he boughte it not, but yet that he gaue ſo manye thouſande crownes, that is to ſaye I boughte not the bread, but I bought the corne. Now this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putacion, if we would go aboute to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyde it by the concylles, and canons of the churche, woulde make an infinite number of biſhops bluſhe and as many curates. Wherinto, Madame, we wold not enter, becauſe we woulde offende no man. And touchinge the article of the holy ſupper of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord we wold not ſpeake ſhe laſte time anye further, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge reſpecte to manye of this compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye, which haue not ben accoſtomed to hear ſpeake of it ſo far, that they ſhuld not eaſely be offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they hear any thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſemeth new &amp; ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:9495:5"/>
And we had rather that they ſhuld vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the language of the auncient doctours of the church then ours, ſeing ſpeciallye that my Lorde Cardynall of Lorrain was bound by open promeſſe, to inſtructe and teache vs, namely vpon this article by the words of the doctors which haue written the firſte fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth years: in ſuche wyſe that we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared oure ſelues bothe with God and with our ſelues for to receiue the light, if it were ſhewed vs, that hetherto it hadde bene hydden frome vs. Nowe for to ſatiſfy our expectation, and of a great part of Chriſtendome they haue propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto vs the article of the holy ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, cut &amp; diminiſhed of the moſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall and neceſſary points and thei haue ſayd vnto vs, ſigne and ſubſcribe vnto this, if not, we wil go no further. If we were preſented vnto you as priſoners, for to haue iudgement geuen vpon vs, yet you woulde not ſaye, ſigne this, if not we condempe you. Your eſtate my Lords byndeth you to ſpeake otherwiſe and commaundeth you to ſhew vs our
<pb facs="tcp:9495:5"/>
erroures, if their be any in vs and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth you to be: <hi>Potentes exhortari in doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na ſana,</hi> thoſe that haue neede of doctrine whiche are readye too geue a reaſon of theyr fayth by the ſcripture: and if the maner of condempninge vs be new, the meane whiche men woulde vſe, would ſeme yet more ſtraunge as we wyll de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare a none.</p>
            <p>Madame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> We are heare preſented vntoo you, for twoo principall endes and purpoſes: the one is to render a reaſon, both to God, to you and to the worlde, of oure fayth. The other for to ſerue God, the kinge and you, by all meanes to vs poſſible forto appeaſe the troubles that are rayſed in the matter of religion. If you ſende vs a waye, and not appoyntinge vs with whome we may freendly conferre, ther ſhall be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge done vnto vs but it wyll be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed thorowe out all Chriſtendome: and ſo it ſhould not be a meane to quiet and apeaſe the troubles: and thoſe that woulde it ſo, knowe it well ynoughe. If you hadde not to do with other than
<pb facs="tcp:9495:6"/>
with vs heare preſente, there were no greate daunger too vſe the matter ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge to the worlde, as a man lyſte: but it ſhall pleaſe you to conſyder that we are heare in the behalfe of a mylli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of men whiche are in this realme, in Swyſſerlande, in Polonia, in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manye, in Englande, and in Scotland, whiche looke all for ſome good reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this aſſemblye, and wyll vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande that in ſteade of conference, as it was promiſed, men geue vs the tenth parte of an article, and ſay, ſigne this, if not, we wyl wade no further. And if we did ſygne that, what ſhoulde they wynne: They that haue ſente vs hyther will know if we were conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by force or els vainquiſhed by good or certayne argumentes. Wherfore we humblye beſeche you (Madame) not to breake of or interrupt this good worke, but geue vs men, that wyll not make any conſcience to confer with vs: other wiſe youre maieſtye mighte iudge of it your ſelf what great occaſion of offence this manner of proceadinge, that they
<pb facs="tcp:9495:6"/>
would ſet foreward, wil bringe with it. And yet becauſe they ſhall not remaine without an anſwer to that which hath bene proponed vnto vs, we declare and ſhewe, that we approue and allow all that hath ben ſpoken by. M. deſpenſe, in the booke, that he hathe geuen vs, without anye other conference.</p>
            <p>And as concerning the article that my Lord Cardinall hath geuen vs, it is but an extracte &amp; declaration of the confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Auſpurge, wherin there are manye things to conſider and way: that is that he ſhould haue geuen vs the whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For it is no reaſon to geue vs one line of an article and leaue oute all the reſte. Moreouer, we ſhould haue kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen if my Lord Cardinall did preſente it of him ſelfe (whiche neuertheleſſe we do not preſume: but deſire to knowe it) or if it be by the autoritye of My Lords the prelates that menne laye before vs the confeſſion Auſpurge, and to aſſure vs ſo thereof that we maye freelye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre togeyther, for that waye at the leaſte (whereof wee thanke God)
<pb facs="tcp:9495:7"/>
my Lord Cardinall of Lorrayn and the others wyll paſſe and alowe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of tranſubſtantiation, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is reproued and reiected by the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon aſſent of all the reformed churches as well in Germanye as elles where. And if they wyll that we ſhall ſygne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye thinge, it is reaſon that my Lorde Cardinall of Lorrayne ſygne alſo that whiche he geueth vs in the name of the companye, to the entent that our chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and congregations whiche haue ſente vs hether, maye ſee and knowe, that we conferre not in vayne. But if my Lorde Cardinall of Lorrayne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in this mynde to come neere vnto the confeſſion of the Allemayns, I truſt that God wil bring vs nere and Ioyne vs together to ſo good a poynte and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect that you ſhall therewyth be content and that his name ſhall thereby be gloryfied throughoute all the worlde. And in the meane whyle Madame, we ſaye that oure Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, is in the holy ſupper wherin he preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, geueth and exhibiteth vnto vs tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
<pb facs="tcp:9495:7"/>
his bodye and bloud by the working of his holy ſpirit. We receaue and eate ſpirituallye and by faythe, that verye bloude which was ſhedde for vs, for to make vs bones of his bones and fleſh of his fleſh, to the end to be quickend ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by and to receiue all that which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for oure ſaluation. And if thys content you not, Madame, but nedeth a greater declaration (as in deede it is daungerouſe and harde too ſpeake of ſo greate a myſterye wyth fewe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des) if it pleaſe my Lorde Cardinall of Lorrayn to performe that he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſed, which is that we ſerche toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the holye ſcriptures, and the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciente doctours of the churche, ſo farre as they be conformable vnto Goddes worde. And alſo if it pleaſe youre ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtye to eſtabliſhe (as you maye doe) a good forme and manner of conference, and certayne deputies, diſputinge in order, hauinge the bookes in preſence with Secretaryes to collecte and write all in a good and auctentike forme. We wyll geue you to vnderſtand and know
<pb facs="tcp:9495:8"/>
that we are not come hyther for to trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the worlde: But for to agree vppon a ſounde doctrine, for hauinge firſt clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed agayne this holye ſacrament with that of the whiche it was ſpoyled, and hauinge taken frome it ſo many things as were added vnto it, we pretende no other thinge, nor deſire any more effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſlye than that it may be eſtabliſhed agayne in his owne perfe<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ion. And to come to this ende, Madame, we geue and offer, in all humilitye to God, and to youre maieſty, and to the reſt &amp; quietnes of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and namely of this realme, our ſoules and our own liues. Prayſed be God.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:9495:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>¶The thurſday laſt of ſeptember.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>WE do beleue that in the holye ſupper oure ſauioure Ieſus Chriſt doeth geue, preſente, and offer vnto vs the ſubſtaunce of his body &amp; bloud by the operation and wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kinge of the holy ghoſt, that we eat and receaue, ſacramentallye, and ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye by fayth, the ſame bodye which is deadde for vs, for to be a bone of hys bones, and fleſhe of hys fleſhe, too the ende that we maye be viuified and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue all that is requiſit to our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And becauſe that the word of God, wherupon our fayth is ſtayed doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and ſet foorth vnto vs his true and naturall body by the holy ghoſt. In this reſpecte, we do rekogniſe and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that the bodye and bloude of our ſauioure Ieſu Chriſt is the ſupper. By theſe words (beyng taken in this ſenſe) being in the ende of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid article we do vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we do aprehend this great &amp; excellent miſtery by faith, which is of ſuch, vertu &amp; efficacy, that it maketh the things that are abſent preſent vnto vs.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
